<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Pelure</title>
  <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-11-23T03:21:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://hugoduncan.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Hugo Duncan</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>http://hugoduncan.org/post/alembic_reloads_your_project_clj_dependencies.html</id>
    <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/post/alembic_reloads_your_project_clj_dependencies.html"/>
    <title>Alembic Reloads your Leiningen project.clj Dependencies</title>
    <summary>When working on a project, you sometime need to add a dependency.  Using Alembic you can add the dependency in your project.clj file, and then call alembic.still/load-project to load the dependency into a running repl, without loosing your repl state.</summary>
    <updated>2013-08-29T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>You're working away in a Clojure REPL, when you realise you need to add a dependency.  You add the dependency to your <a href='[http://leiningen.org](http://leiningen.org)' title='Leiningen'>leiningen</a> <code>project.clj</code> file and then?  Instead of shutting down your REPL, loosing whatever state you have built up, you can use <a href='[https://github.com/pallet/alembic#alembic](https://github.com/pallet/alembic#alembic)' title='Alembic'>Alembic</a> to load the new dependencies.  Simply call <code>&#40;alembic.still/load-project&#41;</code>.</p><p>Of course, it still has to work within the confines of the JVM's classloaders, so you can only add dependencies, and not modify versions or remove dependencies, but this should still cover a lot of use cases.</p><p>To use alembic on a single project, simply add it as a dependency in your <code>:dev</code> profile in <code>project.clj</code>:</p><pre><code class="clj">:profiles {:dev {:dependencies &#91;&#91;alembic &quot;0.2.0&quot;&#93;&#93;}}
</code></pre><p>To make alembic available in all your projects, and it to the <code>:user</code> profile in <code>&#126;/.lein/profiles.clj</code> instead:</p><pre><code class="clj">{:user {:dependencies &#91;&#91;alembic &quot;0.2.0&quot;&#93;&#93;}}
</code></pre><p>Alembic also allows you to directly add dependencies without editing your <code>project.clj</code> file, using the <code>distill</code> function.  Use this if you are just exploring libraries, for example.</p><p>Finally a big thank you to <a href='[http://blog.raynes.me/](http://blog.raynes.me/)' title='Raynes'>Anthony Grimes</a> and the other <a href='[https://github.com/flatland/](https://github.com/flatland/)' title='flatland'>flatland</a> developers for removing classlojure's dependency on <code>useful</code>, which should make this all much more robust.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
