<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Pelure</title>
  <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/index.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-11-15T01:45:47+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://hugoduncan.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Hugo Duncan</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>http://hugoduncan.org/post/rails_environments_for_lisp.html</id>
    <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/post/rails_environments_for_lisp.html"/>
    <title>Rails Environments For Lisp</title>
    <summary>The facility of Ruby on Rails' test, development and production environments is one of those features that goes almost unremarked, but which makes using rails more pleasant.  No doubt everyone has their own solution for this in other environments, and while I am sure Common Lisp is not lacking in examples, I have not seen an idiomatic implementation.  In developing cl-blog-generator I came up with the following solution.</summary>
    <updated>2009-04-07T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><p>The facility of Ruby on Rails' test, development and production environments is one of those features that goes almost unremarked, but which makes using rails more pleasant.  No doubt everyone has their own solution for this in other environments, and while I am sure Common Lisp is not lacking in examples, I have not seen an idiomatic implementation.  In developing <a href="http://github.com/hugoduncan/cl-blog-generator">cl-blog-generator</a> I came up with the following solution.</p> <p>Configuration in Common Lisp usually depends on using special variables, which can be rebound across any block of code.  I started by putting the configuration of my blog into s-expressions in files, but got tired of specifying the file names for different blogs.  Instead, I created an association list for each configuration, and registered each using a symbol as key.  I can now switch to a given environment by specifying the symbol for the environment. </p> <p>The implementation (in <code>src/configure.lisp</code> under the <a href="http://github.com/hugoduncan/cl-blog-generator">GitHub repository</a>) consists of two functions and a special variable.  <code>SET-ENVIRONMENT</code> is used to register an environment, and <code>CONFIGURE</code> is used to make an environment active.  The environments are stored in <code><em>ENVIRONMENTS</em></code> special as an association list.  An example of setting up the configurations can be seen in the <code>config.lisp</code> file.  In creating the configurations I drop the '*' from the special names.</p> <p>I'm relatively new to CL, so let me now if I have overlooked anything.  Writing this post makes me think I am missing a <code>WITH-ENVIRONMENT</code> macro ...</p></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://hugoduncan.org/post/frameworks_and_productivity.html</id>
    <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/post/frameworks_and_productivity.html"/>
    <title>Frameworks and Productivity</title>
    <summary>Yesterday was frustrating; I spent far too long trying to debug some problems in a Rails application I am writing.  Rails, and frameworks in general, are supposed to give us improved productivity by hiding the complexity and mechanics of the task at hand.  This is great as long as the framework behaves as expected, but invariably causes problems when things go wrong.</summary>
    <updated>2009-03-20T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><p>Yesterday was frustrating; I spent far too long trying to debug some problems in a Rails application I am writing.  Rails, and frameworks in general, are supposed to give us improved productivity by hiding the complexity and mechanics of the task at hand.  This is great as long as the framework behaves as expected, but invariably causes problems when things go wrong.</p> <h2>The missing field</h2> My application uses associations, and I had a <code>belongs<i>to</code> association that was supposed to be populated in a <code>before</i>validation<i>on</i>create</code> callback.  In my tests I noticed that the linked model was not being instantiated.  After much searching, it turns out I had forgotten to create the foreign key field.  Unfortunately Rails was silent on this issue and the <code>belongs_to</code> association code seemed to execute quite happily without the field. <h2>Can't dup NilClass</h2> My models also use <code>has_many</code> associations, which I could populate with no problems.  When I tried to access the association though, I kept getting <code>Can't dup NilClass</code> errors.  This one turned out to be an issue with the generated <code>collection.build</code> method.  As noted in the documentation by the somewhat cryptic <cite>Note: This only works if an associated object already exists, not if it‘s nil!</cite>, the method fails if the collection is empty (at least that's what I think it means). Explicitly instantiating the associated model and then adding it to the collection fixed the problem. <h2>Bad choice of name</h2> <p>In my application I had a model named <code>Target</code>, which meant that models that associate with <code>Target</code>, such as my <code>TargetProfile</code> model, have a <code>target</code> attribute.</p>  Unfortunately the <code>target</code> attribute in <code>TargetProfile</code> always returned the instance of <code>TargetProfile</code> - not quite what is expected.  The problem was caused by the fact that <code>ActiveRecord</code>'s <code>AssociationProxy</code>, used to implement associations between models, has a <code>target</code> attribute.  The documentation contains another warning <cite>Don‘t create associations that have the same name as instance methods of ActiveRecord::Base</cite>, but mentions nothing of <code>AssociationProxy</code>, which isn't even part of the documented api.  I call this broken encapsulation. <h2>The Rails Way</h2> Rails heavily promotes testing and Test Driven Development (TDD), which is linked to the "fail early, fail fast" paradigm.  It seems strange that known issues (as partially documented) are allowed to persist and cause silent failures.  All the issues above could have been flagged by Rails. <h2>Conclusion</h2> I am not picking on Rails, however, as these type of issues seem to occur in many frameworks.  No software is bug free, and a framework has to work hard to hide the complexity and mechanics of its domain.  When things go wrong, we are always left questioning whether the issue is in the framework or in our application and we invariably end up getting to know the implementation details of the framework, which does little for our productivity.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://hugoduncan.org/post/parsing_yaml_dates_in_rails_gives_surprising_results.html</id>
    <link href="http://hugoduncan.org/post/parsing_yaml_dates_in_rails_gives_surprising_results.html"/>
    <title>Parsing YAML Dates in Rails Gives Surprising Results</title>
    <summary>Today's surprise was that "2009-01-01" and "2009-1-1" get parsed differently by the YAML parser in Rails.  The former gets converted to a Date&gt;, while the latter becomes a String.  It confused me for a while, as the problem only showed up when I wanted to send the dates to a Flot chart.  Looking at the standard, it's conforming behaviour.   Must be me that is non-conforming then...</summary>
    <updated>2009-03-07T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><p>Today's surprise was that "2009-01-01" and "2009-1-1" get parsed differently by the <a href="http://www.yaml.org/">YAML</a> parser in <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a>.  The former gets converted to a <code>Date</code>, while the latter becomes a <code>String</code>.  It confused me for a while, as the problem only showed up when I wanted to send the dates to a <a href="http://code.google.com/p/flot/">Flot</a> chart.  Looking at the standard, it's conforming behaviour.   Must be me that is non-conforming then...</p></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
